# LEI ZHANG

Chinese University of Hong Kong, Department of Mathematics Room 333B, Science Centre North Block, CUHK, Shatin, Hong Kong  $+852 \cdot 394~35139 \diamond lzhang@math.cuhk.edu.hk$ 

## PERSONAL INFORMATION

DATE OF BIRTH July 16, 1983

GENDER Male

CITIZENSHIP German

## MATHEMATICAL INTERESTS

My area of research is algebraic arithmetic geometry, using techniques from Tannakian categories and affine gerbes.

More specifically, I am interested in non-neutral Tannakian categories, Nori fundamental gerbes, the homotopy sequence of various fundamental groups.

## **EMPLOYMENT**

THE CHINESE UNIVERSITY OF HONG KONG

Oct. 23. 2018 - Present

Research Assistant Professor

Freie Universität Berlin

Nov. 01. 2012 - Oct. 22, 2018

Post-doc

Universität Duisburg-Essen

Jul. 17. 2012 - Sep. 30. 2012

Post-doc

#### **EDUCATION**

Universität Duisburg-Essen

Oct. 01. 2009 - Jul. 16. 2012

Ph.D student under the supervision of Professor Hélène Esnault

Thesis title: The homotopy sequence for fundamental groups

AWARDED: July 16, 2012

CAPITAL NORMAL UNIVERSITY

Sep. 2006 - Jun. 2009

Master Student under the supervision of Professor Kezheng Li

Thesis title: Left Invariant Differential Operators

Degree awarded by College of Mathematical Science in June 2009.

CHINA UNIVERSITY OF MINING AND TECHNOLOGY

Sep. 2002 - Jun. 2006

Bachelor student in Financial Mathematics

Degree awarded by College of Science in June 2006.

#### PREPRINTS AND PUBLICATIONS

- (1) The Homotopy Sequence for Nori's Fundamental Group. Journal of Algebra, Vol. 393, pp. 79 91, 2013. doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jalgebra.2013.07.010
- (2) The Homotopy Sequence for the Algebraic Fundamental Group. International Mathematics Research Notices, no. 22, 6155-6174, 2013. doi: 10.1093/imrn/rnt163
- (3) Nori's Fundamental Group over a non-algebraically Closed Field.
  Annali della Scuola Normale Superiore di Pisa Classe di Scienze (5), 18, no. 4, 1349–1394, 2018. doi: 10.2422/2036-2145.201604\_007
- (4) Algebraic and Nori Fundamental Gerbes (with Fabio Tonini). Journal of the Institute of Mathematics of Jussieu, 1-43, 2017 doi:10.1017/S147474801700024X
- (5) F-divided sheaves trivialized by dominant maps are essentially finite (with Fabio Tonini). Transactions of the American Mathematical Society, 371, 1-22, 2019. doi: https://doi.org/10.1090/tran/7444
- (6) Essentially Finite Vector Bundles on Normal Pseudo-proper Algebraic Stacks (with Fabio Tonini). https://arxiv.org/abs/1702.03751.
- (7) Nori fundamental gerbe of essentially finite covers and Galois closure of towers of torsors (with M. Antei, I. Biswas, M. Emsalem, F. Tonini). To appear in Selecta Mathematica, https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.00739.
- (8) Neukirch-Uchida Theorem for Purely Inseparable Field Extensions (with M. Romagny, F. Tonini). https://arxiv.org/pdf/1711.06898.pdf.
- (9) A crystalline version of Berthelot's conjecture (with V. Di Proietto, F. Tonini). In preparation.

## PROFESSIONAL SERVICES

- (1) Referee of Mathematical Research Letters
- (2) Referee of Journal of Topology
- (3) Referee of American Journal of Mathematics
- (4) Referee of Compositio Mathematica.
- (5) Reviewer of zbMATH.

#### INVITED SEMINAR TALKS

- (1) Number Theory Seminar at Capital Normal University, 08/2011. Invited by Prof. Dr. Kezheng Li and Dr. Zifeng Yang.
- (2) Number Theory Seminar at Capital Normal University, 03/2012. Invited by Prof. Dr. Kezheng Li and Dr. Zifeng Yang.
- (3) Arithmetic Geometry Seminar at Universität Regensburg, 30/11/2012. Invited by Prof. Dr. Uwe Jannsen.
- (4) Séminaire de géométrie algébrique at IRMAR Université de Rennes 1, 03/10/2013. Invited by Prof. Dr. Matthieu Romagny.

- (5) Scuola Normale Superiore di Pisa, 20/11/2013. Invited by Prof. Dr. Angelo Vistoli.
- (6) Séminaire de Théorie des Nombres at Institut de Mathématiques de Bordeaux, 11/04/2014. Invited by Dr. Jilong Tong.
- (7) Number Theory Seminar at Capital Normal University, 08/10/2014.
- (8) Séminaire d'algèbre, topologie et géométrie at Laboratoire J. A. Dieudonné, Université de Nice, 18/12/2014. Invited by Dr. Macro Antei.
- (9) Number Theory Seminar at Capital Normal University, 30/03/2017.
- (10) Colloquium talk at SUSTech, 07/01/2018.
- (11) Geometry Seminar at SUN YAT-SEN UNIVERSITY, 08/01/2018.
- (12) Colloquium talk at National Tsing Hua University (Hsinchu), 12/03/2018.
- (13) Seminar talk at National Center for Theoretical Science (Hsinchu), 14/03/2018. Invited by Prof. Dr. Chieh-Yu Chang.
- (14) Colloquium talk at the Department of Mathematics of Hong Kong University, 07.03.2018.
- (15) Colloquium talk at the Department of Mathematics of the Chinese University of Hong Kong, 16.04.2018.

#### CONFERENCE TALKS

DEUTSCHEN MATHEMATIKER-VEREINIGUNG at Universität des Saarlandes, Saarbrücken.

Sep.17, 2012 - Sep. 20, 2012

On the Homotopy Sequence of Nori's Fundamental Group. (Minisymposia and Sections Sep.17, 2012)

NORTH GERMAN ALGEBRAIC GEOMETRY SEMINAR at Universität Hamburg, Hamburg.

May 15, 2014 - May 16, 2014

Galois Theory for Schemes. (May 16, 2014)

ARITHMÉTIQUE DES VARIÉTÉS EN FAMILLES at Institut de Mathématiques de Bordeaux.

Nov. 4, 2014 - Nov. 7, 2014

Nori's Fundamental Group with a Geometric Point. (Nov. 5, 2014)

CURVES AND GROUPS IN FAMILIES at Henri Lebesgue Center, Rennes.

May 13, 2019 - Nov. 17, 2019

Fundamental group schemes en caracteristic p. (May, 2019)

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

- (1) Exercise session for the course Algebraic Number Theory II, Freie Universität Berlin, summer semester 2018.
- (2) Seminar: Quadratische Formen (in English Quadratic Forms), Freie Universität Berlin, summer semester 2018. This seminar was in German.
- (3) Course: Crystals and Crystalline Cohomology, Freie Universität Berlin, winter semester 2017.
- (4) Seminar: *p-adische Zahlen* (in English *p-adic Numbers*), Freie Universität Berlin, summer semester 2017. This seminar was in German.
- (5) Exercise session for the course Algebraic Number Theory II, Freie Universität Berlin, summer semester 2017.
- (6) Course: Étale Cohomology, Freie Universität Berlin, winter semester 2016-2017.
- (7) Course: Algebraic Groups, Freie Universität Berlin, summer semester 2016.
- (8) Seminar: Analytic Methods in Number Theory, Freie Universität Berlin, winter semester 2015-2016.
- (9) Exercise session for the course Elliptic Curves, Freie Universität Berlin, winter semester 2015-2016.
- (10) Seminar: Quadratic Forms, Freie Universität Berlin, summer semester 2015.
- (11) Exercise session for the course Algebraic Number Theory II, Freie Universität Berlin, summer semester 2015.
- (12) Exercise session for the course Algebraic Number Theory II, Freie Universität Berlin, winter semester 2014-2015.
- (13) Student seminar p-adic Numbers, Freie Universität Berlin, winter semester 2014-2015.
- (14) Teaching assistant of Prof. Dr. Hélène Esnault for the master course Algebraic Number Theory, Freie Universität Berlin, summer semester 2014.
- (15) Teaching assistant of Prof. Dr. Hélène Esnault for the master course Commutative Algebra I, Freie Universität Berlin, winter semester 2013-2014.
- (16) Teaching assistant of Prof. Dr. Hélène Esnault for the master course Algebraic Number Theory II, Freie Universität Berlin, summer semester 2013.
- (17) Lern- und Diskussionszentren (LuDi), Universität Duisburg-Essen, summer semester 2012.
- (18) Teaching assistant of Prof. Dr. Hélène Esnault and Prof. Dr. Moritz Kerz for the master course Algebraic Geometry III, Universität Duisburg-Essen, summer semester 2011.

## **STUDENTS**

- (1) 2018, Ragnarsson Amazeen, master thesis: Étale and Proétale Fundamental Groups, Freie Universität Berlin.
- (2) 2018, Janine Schuhmann, bachelor thesis: Klassifikation von quadratischen Form über  $\mathbb{Q}_p$ ,  $\mathbb{Q}$  und  $\mathbb{R}$

## LANGUAGE SKILLS

- (1) Chinese (native)
- (2) English (fluent)
- (3) German (fluent)
- (4) French (basic)